Zuokun OUYANG Ph.D.

+33 (0)6 50 32 30 04 zuokun.ouyang@outlook.com https://alainouyang.github.io zuokun-ouyang

Recently graduated with a Ph.D., I specialize in the fusion of econometrics and machine learning, particularly in the field of time series forecasting. My research encompasses time series analysis, econometric-machine learning integration, and sequential/temporal learning.

EDUCATION

University of Orléans

Ph.D., Computer Science and Signal Processing

Orléans, France

Oct. 2019 – July 2023

- Dissertation: Time Series Forecasting: From Econometrics to Deep Learning
- Supervisors: Prof. Philippe Ravier, Assoc. Prof. Meryem Jabloun
- Funding: Association Nationale de la Recherche et de la Technologie CIFRE N° 2019/0551 contracted with ATTILA Gestion

University of Orléans

Orléans, France

Diplôme d'Ingénieur, Computer Engineering, *Polytech Orléans* **M.Sc., Computer Science**

Sept. 2015 – June 2018

- Sept. 2017 June 2018
- Dissertation: A Fundamental Study on Deep Learning based Time Series Forecasting
 Supervisors: Prof. Christel Vrain, Prof. Marcilio C. P. de Souto, Assoc. Prof. Sylvie Treuillet

BEIJING INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY B.Eng., Electrical & Electronics Engineering

Beijing, China

Sept. 2012 - June 2016

- Dissertation: A Microphone Array-based System for Sound Source Localization
- Supervisors: Assoc. Prof. Shiyong Li, Assoc. Prof. Rodolphe Weber

Professional Experience

University of Orléans

Orléans, France

Temporary Research Assistant & Assistant Lecturer (ATER)

Jan. 2023 – Present

- Signals and Linear Systems (EPL3CI13).
- Embedded Systems Projects (EPL2CI03).
- Introduction to Signal Processing (EPL4CI04).
- Mathematics and Computer Science Basics (EPL2CI13).
- Acquisition Systems and Signal Processing (EPL2IA01).

ATTILA GESTION

Lyon & Montargis, France Oct. 2019 – Dec. 2022

Machine Learning Engineer and Data Analyst

- Identified and assessed various internal metrics across multiple franchise agencies.
- Designed multi-step forecasting models for multivariate time series.
- Performed customer segmentation exploiting traditional and time series clustering techniques.
- Developed pipelines for assessing the effectiveness of various time series forecasting models.

ATTILA GESTION Data Analyst Intern

Montargis, France *Apr.* 2018 – Sept. 2018

- Evaluated performance metrics of numerous franchise agencies.
- Performed a literature review on econometric and ML models for time series analysis.
- Investigated and assessed different econometric and ML models for time series forecasting.

ECONTENT STORE SARL Software Development Engineer Intern

Luxembourg

June 2017 – Aug. 2017

- Acted as one of the core developers of the Android development team.
- Implemented key enhancements and upgrades for AR functionalities, encompassing improved technique selection, natural feature training pipeline, and numerous bug fixes.
- Led the development of a user-end WebGL tool for natural features training to improve rendering performance.

SCIENTIFIC. Knowledge

Programming Python, R, C#, Java, C/C++, Swift, MATLAB, SQL

Frameworks & Tools PyTorch, scikit-learn, Unity3D, OpenCV, PowerBI, Linux, Git

Skills & Expertise Deep Learning, Machine Learning, Time Series Analysis, Signal Processing, Optimization Theory, Non-linear Regression

Languages English (proficient), French (proficient), Mandarin (native)

SELECTED **PUBLICATIONS**

- 1. Z. Ouyang, M. Jabloun, and P. Ravier, "Leveraging Rank Correlation and STL Decomposition for Transformer-based Time Series Forecasting," Expert Syst. Appl., in preparation, 2023.
- 2. Z. Ouyang, M. Jabloun, and P. Ravier, "A Contemporary and Comprehensive Survey on Time Series Forecasting," IEEE Trans. Knowl. Data Eng., in preparation, 2023.
- 3. Z. Ouyang, M. Jabloun, and P. Ravier, "STLformer: Exploit STL decomposition and Rank Correlation for Time Series Forecasting," in *Proc. EUSIPCO*, 2023.

 4. **Z. Ouyang**, M. Jabloun, and P. Ravier, "Rankformer: Leverage Rank Correlation for Transformer-
- based Time Series Forecasting," in *Proc. IEEE SSP*, 2023.
- 5. G. Ouyang, K. Abed-Meraim, and **Z. Ouyang**, "Magnetic-Field-Based Indoor Positioning Using Temporal Convolutional Networks," Sensors, vol. 23, no. 3, p. 1514, 2023.
- 6. **Z. Ouyang**, P. Ravier, and M. Jabloun, "Are Deep Learning Models Practically Good as Promised? A Strategic Comparison of Deep Learning Models for Time Series Forecasting," in Proc. EU-SIPCO, 2022.
- 7. Z. Ouyang, P. Ravier, and M. Jabloun, "A Comparison Study of Deep Learning Models Combined with Multistep Time Series Forecasting Strategies," in *Proc. ITISE*, 2022, p. 2.
- 8. Z. Ouyang, P. Ravier, and M. Jabloun, "STL Decomposition of Time Series Can Benefit Forecasting Done by Statistical Methods but Not by Machine Learning Ones," Eng. Proc., vol. 5, no. 1, p. 42, 2021.

SELECTED **PROJECTS**

iOS application RestauRank

Mar. 2018 – Apr. 2018

- Developed a map App to locate top-rated local restaurants and determine the fastest route.
- Google Maps SDK and Google Geolocation API for map visualization, navigation, and reviews.

Archaeological ceramic decoration segmentation

Jan. 2018 – Mar. 2018

- Built 2D FCNs to segment decorated regions on ancient ceramic fragments using depth maps.
- Clustered segmented areas and preprocessed depth maps into distinct categories.
- Benchmarked the clustering results against other algorithms, including *K*-means and DBSCAN.

Interactive real-time earthquake map

Apr. 2017 - May 2017

- Developed an interactive map application in Java to display global earthquake information.
- Used *Processing* for UI and icons display, *Unfolding* for user interaction.
- Differentiated locations, depth, levels, and occurrence time with varied icon shapes and colors.

A microphone array-based system for sound source localization

Mar. 2016 - May 2016

- Developed a microphone array system with Python for sound source localization.
- Used Raspberry Pi, Arduino UNO, a stepper motor, and an eight-microphone array.
- Implemented DOA-TDOA & GCC algorithms for sound source localization.

AWARDS

- College Student Academic Scholarship, Beijing Institute of Technology 2012 - 2015National 3rd Prize, Chinese Exhibition of Calligraphy and Painting for Undergraduates 2013
- National 3rd Prize, The 25th Chinese Chemistry Olympiad 2011
- Provincial 1st Prize, The 28th Chinese Physics Olympiad 2011
- Provincial 1st Prize, The 20th China High School Biology Olympiad 2011

OTHER EXPERIENCE • Volunteer, Chinese New Year Festivity, Orléans and Yangzhou Government Feb. 2017 • Vice President, Association of Calligraphy of Beijing Institute of Technology 2013 - 2015

HOBBIES

Basketball, Reading, Chinese Calligraphy, Singing, Fitness, and Cooking.